Guide to the Duke University Union Records, 1954-ongoing
Duke University. University Archives
Dorothy Newsom Rankin papers 1894-1997
Duke University. University Archives
Rankin, Dorothy Newsom, 1911-2002.
4.25 linear feet Extent: approx. 4000 Items
Dorothy Newsom Rankin graduated from Duke University in 1933. The collection includes family papers accumulated by Dorothy Newsom Rankin and her father, D. W. Newsom, related to their ties with and the history of Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) and Duke University.
uarankindorothy
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Dorothy Newsom Rankin Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 2007, 2012.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Newsom Rankin was the daughter of D. W. (Dallas Walton) Newsom (Trinity Class of 1899) and Tempie Battle. She graduated summa cum laude from Duke University in 1933. While a student, she was elected Phi Beta Kappa, served as senior class president of the Woman's College as well as May Day Queen her senior year, and was a member of the Kappa Delta sorority and White Duchy. Dorothy married Professor Robert Rankin shortly after her graduation in 1933. She was actively involved in University life until her death in 2002. She has the distinction of being not only a Duke alumnae, but also a faculty wife, and the daughter, mother, and grandmother of Duke alumni.
Rankin's father, D. W. Newsom attended Trinity College from 1895-1899. While a student, he worked as the personal secretary for President John Kilgo. He also edited the literary magazine The Trinity Archive, was elected Phi Beta Kappa, and was a member of 9019, Kappa Alpha, and Sigma Upsilon. After graduation, Newsom worked as Trinity College's registrar (1901-1907) and treasurer (1907-1923). He died in 1949.
Collection Overview
The collection includes family papers accumulated by Dorothy Newsom Rankin (1911-2002), and her father, D. W. (Dallas Walton) Newsom (1873-1949). It includes correspondence, notes, a student diary by Newsom, clippings, photographs, objects, and other materials relating to Trinity College, Duke University, Kappa Delta sorority, and Phi Kappa Psi. Newsom learned shorthand prior to entering Trinity College. Newsome's diary is written in shorthand but has been translated, a copy of which accompanies the original diary. There are also files about "Marse Jack," the old Trinity College bell on East Campus and the controversy regarding the desire of some to have it moved to West Campus. Dorothy Newsom Rankin lead the charge to keep it on East Campus, the original site of Trinity College.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Rankin, Robert S. (Robert Stanley), 1899-1976; Rankin, Dorothy Newsom, 1911-2002; Newsom, D. W. (Dallas Walton), 1873-1949; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--History -- 19th century; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Alumni and alumnae; Kappa Delta Sorority. Sigma Delta Chapter (Duke University).; Bells -- North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Robert S. Rankin Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert S. Rankin Papers
Duke University Archives
D. W. Newsom Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
D. W. Newsom Papers
Duke University Archives
Kappa Delta Records
Duke University Archives
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (9 boxes)
  - D. W. Newsom: Letters, 1891-1903(4 folders) (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Writings - "To the Men of the Golden Star," 1919 (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Writings - "In Memory of Everybody's Friend 'Marse Jim' (James Haywood Southgate)" and "Caprice," undated, 1897 (Box 1)
  - D.W. Newsom: Writings - "The Philosophy of a Layman," undated (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Postcards and Photographs, circa late 1890's-early 1900's (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Private Account Book, 1895-1900 (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Student Diary, 1898 (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Diary Transcription and Supplemental Information (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Pernin/Piernan's Shorthand Alphabet (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Correspondence re: Chapel Talks and John Kilgo, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
  - D. W. Newsom: Correspondence, 1915, 1948 (Box 2)
  - "The American Illustrated Methodist Magazine," 1901 Jan. (includes article on Trinity College written by Prof. Edwin Mims) (Box 2)
  - Salaries of Officers and Teachers at Trinity College, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
  - Programs, Commencements, Southern Conservatory of Music, Letters, etc., 1890s, 1901-1905 (includes programs from the Academy of Music in Durham) (7 folders) (Box 2)
  - Programs: Duke-Related Productions, Miscellaneous, 1925-1926, 1930's (Box 2)
  - Programs: Duke Chapel Events, 1930's (Box 2)
  - Programs: Commencement, 1930's (Box 2)
  - Programs: Non-Duke Productions, 1930's (includes "A Brief History of Duke Homestead," circa 1936) (Box 2)
  - Programs: Musical Clubs (various), 1930's (Box 2)
  - Programs: Quadrangle Pictures, 1930's, 1940's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Duke Chapel Events, 1940's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Duke-Related Productions, Miscellaneous, 1940's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Musical Clubs (various), 1940's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Duke-Related Productions, 1950's, 1960's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Duke-Related Productions, Miscellaneous, 1970's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Duke Chapel Events, 1970's (Box 3)
  - Programs: Non-Duke Productions, 1970's (Box 3)
  - Edward Hall Broadhead Cantata, 1936, 1939 (Box 3)
  - Class of 1933, 1947-1964 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Fannie Kilgo Groome (and Old Trinity), 1968-1982 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - American Legion Beauty Pageant Program, 1933 (Box 3)
  - White Duchy, 1960-1963 (Box 3)
  - Sewing Club, circa 1930-1992 (Box 4)
  - Campus Club, circa 1946-1956, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Town and Campus Club, circa 1967-1970's, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Trinity Commencement Choir, 1970's-1980's (Box 4)
  - Trinity, 1970's, undated (Box 4)
  - Phi Kappa Psi, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Phi Kappa Psi, 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - Phi Kappa Psi, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Phi Kappa Psi: Photographs, circa 1928-1930's (Box 4)
  - Dept. of Political Science, 1964-1990 (Box 4)
  - Major Seversky: Robert Rankin's Introductory Remarks, introducing the lecturer (he was Chair of Lecture Committee), 1942 (Box 4)
  - "Early History of the Rankin Family," by Robert Rankin, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Flag Raising Tradition, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Nixon Library, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Marse Jack, 1951, 1958, 1982-1983 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Marse Jack, 1958, 1964, 1982-1983 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Marse Jack, 1983-1984, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Marse Jack, 1983-1984, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Marse Jack: Photographs, circa late 1890's/early 1900's, 1970's, 1980's (Box 5)
  - Class of 1959, circa 1959-1984 (Box 5)
  - Kappa Delta Songbook and Sheet Music, 1932, 1936 March (Box 5)
  - Kappa Delta Scrapbook and Account Book, 1930's-1940's (Box 5)
  - Kappa Delta, 1950's (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, 1959-1960 (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, 1960's (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta, undated (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta Publications, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Kappa Delta Publications, 1961-1962 (Box 7)
  - Kappa Delta Pledge Paddle, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Kappa Delta (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Nixon Library (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Trinity/Duke (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Douglas Knight Inauguration (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Marse Jack (Box 7)
  - Clippings: Class of 1959 (Box 7)
  - Photographs and Negatives (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - D. W. Newsom's Trinity College Textbooks (Box 8)
    - "Introduction to the Study of the Middle Ages"
    - "The French Revolution: A History, Vol. II"
    - "The Students' Series of Latin Classics: Exercises in Latin Prose Composition, Part II"
    - "Heroes and Hero Worship"
    - "Hymn Book"
  - Kappa Delta Rush Uniform, circa 1958 (Box 9)